<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
		"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="serviceability">
  <title>Serviceability</title>
  
<para>
	@product.name@ supports two kinds of logging: <emphasis>Event Logging</emphasis> and <emphasis>Trace logging</emphasis> which is usually referred
	to simply as <emphasis>Logging</emphasis>. The difference between Event Logging and Logging is explained below, but both are configured in the <literal>serviceability.xml</literal> file in the <literal>config</literal> directory.
This file takes the form of a Logback configuration—@short.product.name@
uses a Logback implementation behind the SLF4J logging interface.
<para>
For a description of the syntax and facilities provided by <literal>serviceability.xml</literal>
see the <emphasis>Logback</emphasis> documentation (referenced in <xref linkend="furtherreading"/>).
</para> 
</para>

   <section id="serviceability-info-log">
      <title>Event logging</title>
      <para>
        Event logging records important events in @product.name@. Each event is logged to
 		an event log file and is accompanied by a code enclosed in angle brackets. 
 		An example is shown below:
<screen>
[2010-10-25 16:20:45.897] system-artifacts             &lt;TC0010I&gt; Creating HTTP/1.1 connector with scheme http on port 8080.
</screen>
		(For a description of the log code syntax, see <xref linkend="log-codes"/>.)
        The format of event log messages is fully configurable.
      </para>
		<para>
		    By default, event log messages are stored in <literal>$SERVER_HOME/serviceability/eventlogs/eventlog.log</literal>.
      	</para>
		<para>
			The default behaviour is that, once <literal>eventlog.log</literal> reaches a 10Mb limit, it rolls into a series of files named	
			<literal>eventlog_</literal><emphasis>i</emphasis><literal>.log</literal> where <emphasis>i</emphasis> ranges from 1 to 4, and event logging continues in 
			a new <literal>eventlog.log</literal> file.
		</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="serviceability-info-trace">
      <title>(Trace) Logging</title>
      <para>
	    The @product.name@&rsquo;s (trace) logging support serves two main purposes:
	    <itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    It provides global trace files that capture high-volume information regarding the @product.name@&rsquo;s internal events. 
		    The files are intended
		    for use by support personnel to diagnose runtime problems.  
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		    It provides application trace files that contain application-generated output. 
		    This includes output generated using popular logging and
		    tracing APIs, as well as output generated by calls to <literal>System.out</literal> and <literal>System.err</literal>. 
		    These files are
		    intended for use by application developers and system administrators.
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
		    By default, the @short.product.name@ trace file is called 
		    <literal>$SERVER_HOME/serviceability/logs/log.log</literal>,
		    and, again by default, the application trace files are called 
		    <literal>$SERVER_HOME/serviceability/logs/</literal><emphasis>application_name</emphasis><literal>/log.log</literal>, 
            where <emphasis>application_name</emphasis> is automatically set by @short.product.name@ for each application artifact installed and run 
            (it is a combination of the artifact name and the version).
        </para>
		<para>
			The default behaviour of these trace files is that, once <literal>log.log</literal> reaches a 10Mb limit, it rolls into a series of files named	
			<literal>log_</literal><emphasis>i</emphasis><literal>.log</literal> where <emphasis>i</emphasis> ranges from 1 to 4, and logging continues in 
			a new <literal>log.log</literal> file.
		</para>
      <para>
		Entries in trace files are by default of the form &lt;timestamp&gt; &lt;thread-name&gt; &lt;source&gt; &lt;level&gt; &lt;entry-text&gt;. For example:
		<screen>
[2008-05-15 09:09:46.940] server-dm-2 org.apache.coyote.http11.Http11Protocol I Initializing Coyote HTTP/1.1 on http-48080
	    </screen>
        although this format is completely determined by the Logback configuration file <literal>serviceability.xml</literal>.
      </para>
	  <section id="serviceability-info-trace-app">
		<title>Application Output</title>
		<para>
			@product.name@ provides advanced support for capturing and tracing application-generated output by automatically separating trace output on a
			per-application basis and will also capture any <literal>System.out</literal> and <literal>System.err</literal> output.
		</para>
		<section id="per-application-trace">
			<title>Per-application trace</title>
			<para>
				@product.name@ uses SLF4J interfaces to Logback, and the root logger (by default) captures all logging output
				and appends it to the application-specific trace files as described above.
				To modify this, define application-specific loggers in the <literal>serviceability.xml</literal> file in the normal way.
			</para>
        </section>
        <section id="sysout-and-syserr">
	      <title>System.out and System.err</title>
		  <para>
            <literal>System.out</literal> and <literal>System.err</literal> output from applications is, by default, captured in the
            application&rsquo;s trace file.
            This happens because the output streams are intercepted and written to the loggers named 
            <literal>System.out</literal> and <literal>System.err</literal> respectively.  
			Since there are no explicit loggers defined with these names in the <literal>serviceability.xml</literal> file, 
			this output is logged by the root logger (which captures <literal>INFO</literal> level and above).
          </para>
		  <para>
			The capture of <literal>System.out</literal> and <literal>System.err</literal> output is configured in the
			<literal>config/org.eclipse.virgo.medic.properties</literal> file by the <literal>log.wrapSysOut</literal> and 
			<literal>log.wrapSysErr</literal> properties. By default the properties have a value of <literal>true</literal>
			and capture is enabled. Capture can be disabled by configuring the properties with a value of <literal>false</literal>.
		  </para>
          <para>
            The trace entries for <literal>System.out</literal> and <literal>System.err</literal>
			output are of the form:
		    <screen>
[2008-05-16 09:28:45.874] server-tomcat-thread-1 System.out Hello world!
[2008-05-16 09:28:45.874] server-tomcat-thread-1 System.err Hello world!
			</screen>
			The third column indicates where the output came from (<literal>System.out</literal> or <literal>System.err</literal>).
		  </para>
		  <para>
		  To over-ride this behaviour, simply define explicit loggers named <literal>System.out</literal> 
		  and/or <literal>System.err</literal> in the configuration file to send this output to an appender of your choice.
		  Be aware that all applications&rsquo; output streams will be caught by these loggers, and that a sifting appender might be useful to separate them.
		  </para>
		</section>
	  </section>
    </section>
    <section id="serviceability-info-dump">
      <title>Service Dumps</title>
      <para>
        A service dump is triggered when one of the following events
        occurs:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A failure is detected in the @product.name@ code, or
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            a thread deadlock is detected.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        A service dump contains a snapshot of all the important state from
        the running @product.name@ instance. This snapshot is not intended
        for end user consumption but is useful for service personnel.
      </para>
      <para>
        By default, service dumps are created in
        <literal>$SERVER_HOME/serviceability/dump</literal>.
      </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
