<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="server-perspective-views">
	<title>Server Perspective and Views</title>
	<section id="server-perspective">
		<title>Virgo Perspective</title>
		<para>
			The Virgo perspective provides an environment customized to support configuring and running @umbrella.product.name@
			instances, including views for working with @umbrella.product.name.short@s. To switch to the Virgo Perspective from
			your current perspective, select
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu>
				<guisubmenu>Show Perspective</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Other...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			And select "Virgo".
		</para>
		<para>
			<imagedata fileref="images/virgo-perspective.png" format="PNG" />
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="views">
		<title>Views</title>
		<para>
			You can explore the contents of installed servers using the Virgo Server Views. These views are designed to help you
			get to resources on the server without having to switch to the native file system, and integrate those resources with
			other Eclipse IDE tools. (You can also use the Virgo views from within other perspectives, of course. Select
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu>
				<guisubmenu>Show View</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Other...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			and then open the "Virgo" folder to display them.)
		</para>
		<section id="views-respository">
			<title>Repository View</title>
			<para>The Virgo Repository view allows you to work directly with the contents of installed bundles and libraries on
				@product.instance@s.
			</para>
			<para>
				<imagedata fileref="images/views-repository.png" format="PNG" />
			</para>
			<para>To view resources, select a repository in the Servers View. You can customize what and how they are displayed
				using the view toolbar buttons.
			</para>
			<para>You can select multiple respositories as well, allowing you to easily navigate and compare resources on
				multiple servers. You can double-click on items, open them, and even explore class hierchies and other Eclipse
				features by right clicking on the repository resources.
			</para>
			<para>
				<emphasis>Hint:</emphasis>
				In the example below we have selected the Flat Layout and can see that javax.ejb library is present in one
				@umbrella.product.name.short@, but not the other.
			</para>
			<para>
				<imagedata fileref="images/views-repository-example.png" format="PNG" />
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="views-properties">
			<title>Properties View</title>
			<para>The Virgo Properties view allows you to inspect the properties of @product.instance@s. Rather then digging
				through files on the server instance to find the parameters you need to adjust, simply select the server(s) you want
				to find parameters for, and a list of properties files will be displayed in the editor. To open a file in the
				appropriate Eclipse editor, just double-click on it. Or open a tree node and double-click on a specific property and
				the property value will be highlighted for editing.
			</para>
			<para>
				<imagedata fileref="images/views-properties-tree.png" format="PNG" />
			</para>
			<para>
				<emphasis>Hint:</emphasis>
				Not sure where a given property is even located? You can easily see all properties within a given
				@umbrella.product.name.short@
				across all properties files, sorted by name. Click the "List" button in the view
				toolbar. You can even see properties across runtime instances by selecting multiple servers in the Server View.
			</para>
			<para>
				<imagedata fileref="images/views-properties-list.png" format="PNG" />
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="views-logs">
			<title>Logs View</title>
			<para>The Virgo Logs view supports easy access to runtime log files. As with the other views, just select the
				@product.instance@(s) you are interested in. Then double-click to open the relevant log file.
			</para>
			<para>
				<imagedata fileref="images/views-logs.png" format="PNG" />
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="views-console">
			<title>Console View</title>
			<para>The Console view is the same view that is used in the Java and other perspectives. It displays the console
				activity for the last server instance you launched, assuming that you haven't launched another console hosted
				process in the mean-time. (This view is not connected to the Server View -- if you want to examine consoles for
				differnt running servers, click the "Down Triangle" icon in the view toolbar and select the appropriate console.)
			</para>
			<para>
				<imagedata fileref="images/views-logs.png" format="PNG" />
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="views-projects">
		<title>Virgo Server Projects</title>
		<para>To support all of the view features, projects are created within your workspace. These are managed automatically
			and shouldn't be modified, deleted or renamed. But you can explore these artifacts directly from the project and
			package explorers and with other Eclipse tools.
		</para>
		<para>
			<emphasis>Hint:</emphasis>
			For example, you can find out what classes are available on Virgo Servers using the Type and Resource search
			dialogs. Just select
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Navigate</guimenu>
				<guisubmenuitem>Open Type...</guisubmenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			and enter a search pattern.
		</para>
		<para>
			<imagedata fileref="images/views-open-type-dialog.png" format="PNG" />
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
