<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
		"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="architecture">
	<title>Deployment Architecture</title>
	<para>
		The @product.name@
		offers several choices when it comes to deploying applications. Each choice offers certain advantages, and it is
		important to understand those in order to make the right choice for your application. In this chapter, we take a
		closer look at the choices offered, compare them, and provide guidelines in choosing the right one based on your
		specific needs. 
	</para>
	<para>
		The @short.product.name@ supports standard self-contained WAR files thus allowing you to use the @product.name@
		as an enhanced web server. The @short.product.name@ also supports the 
		<emphasis>Shared Libraries</emphasis>
		WAR format which allows for slimmer WAR files that depend on OSGi bundles instead of including JAR files inside the
		WAR. The
		<emphasis>Shared Services</emphasis>
		WAR format allows developers to further reduce the complexity of standard WARs by deploying services and
		infrastructure bundles alongside the WAR. A shared services WAR will then consume the services published by those
		bundles. To complete the picture, the @short.product.name@ supports the new OSGi-standard
		<emphasis>Web Bundle</emphasis>
		deployment format for web applications that builds on the benefits provided by a shared services WAR. In addition
		to this @short.product.name@ provides additional conveniences for developing and deploying Spring MVC-based web
		applications.
	</para>
	<para>For applications consisting of multiple bundles and web applications, plans and the PAR format are the
		primary deployment models that take advantage of OSGi capabilities. We will explore all of these formats and their
		suitability later in this guide.</para>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<!-- ======================================================================= -->
	<section id="architecture-deployment-formats">
		<title>Supported Deployment Formats</title>
		<para>
			The @product.name@
			supports applications packaged in the following formats: 
		</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><link linkend="architecture-raw-osgi-bundles">Raw OSGi Bundles</link></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><link linkend="architecture-wars">Java EE WAR</link></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><link linkend="architecture-war-rfc66">Web Bundles</link></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><link linkend="architecture-pars">PAR</link></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><link linkend="architecture-plans">Plans</link></para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>
			When you deploy an application to the @short.product.name@, each deployment artifact (e.g., a single bundle, WAR, PAR, or
			plan) passes through a deployment pipeline. This deployment pipeline supports the notion of personality-specific
			deployers which are responsible for processing an application with a certain personality (i.e., application type).
			The @bundle.version@ release of the @short.product.name@ natively supports personality-specific deployers analogous
			to each of the aforementioned packaging options. Furthermore, the deployment pipeline can be extended with additional
			personality deployers, and future releases of the @short.product.name@ will provide support for personalities such as
			Batch, Web Services, etc.
		</para>
		<para>
			Let&rsquo;s take a closer look now at each of the supported deployment and packaging options to explore which one is best
			suited for your applications.
		</para>
		<section id="architecture-raw-osgi-bundles">
			<title>Raw OSGi Bundles</title>
			<para>
				At its core, the @product.name@
				is an OSGi container. Thus any OSGi-compliant bundle can be deployed directly on the @short.product.name@ unmodified.
				You&rsquo;ll typically deploy an application as a single bundle or a set of stand-alone bundles if you&rsquo;d like to publish or
				consume services globally within the container via the OSGi Service Registry. 
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="architecture-wars">
			<title>WAR Deployment Formats</title>
			<para>
				For Web Application Archives (WAR), the @product.name@
				provides support for the following three formats. 
			</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><link linkend="architecture-standard-war">Standard WAR</link></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><link linkend="architecture-shared-libraries-war">Shared Libraries WAR</link></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><link linkend="architecture-shared-services-war">Shared Services WAR</link></para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para> Each of these formats plays a distinct role in the incremental migration path from a standard Java EE WAR to
				an OSGi-ified web application.</para>
			<section id="architecture-standard-war">
				<title>Standard WAR</title>
				<para>
					Standard WAR files are supported directly in the @short.product.name@. At deployment time, the WAR file is
					transformed into an OSGi bundle and installed into Tomcat. All the standard WAR contracts are honored, and your
					existing WAR files should just drop in and deploy without change. Support for standard, unmodified WAR files
					allows you to try out the @product.name@ on your existing web applications and then gradually migrate toward the
					<emphasis>Shared Libraries WAR</emphasis>
					and
					<emphasis>Shared Services WAR</emphasis>
					formats.
				</para>
				<para> In addition to the standard support for WARs that you would expect from Tomcat, the @short.product.name@ also
					enables the following features:</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Spring-driven load-time weaving (see Section 6.8.4, “Load-time weaving with AspectJ in the
							Spring Framework").</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Diagnostic information such as FFDC (first failure data capture)</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
				<para> The main benefit of this application style is familiarity -- everyone knows how to create a WAR file! You can
					take advantage of the @short.product.name@&rsquo;s added feature set without modifying the application. The application
					can also be deployed on other Servlet containers or Java EE application servers.</para>
				<para>
					You may choose this application style if the application is fairly simple and small. You may also prefer this style
					even for large and complex applications as a starting point and migrate to the other styles over time as discussed
					in
					<xref linkend="migrating-to-osgi" />
					.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section id="architecture-shared-libraries-war">
				<title>Shared Libraries WAR</title>
				<para>
					If you have experience with developing and packaging web applications using the standard WAR format, you&rsquo;re
					certainly familiar with the pains of library bloat. So, unless you&rsquo;re installing shared libraries in a common
					library folder for your Servlet container, you have to pack all JARs required by your web application in
					<literal>/WEB-INF/lib</literal>. 
					Prior to the release of the @product.name@, such library bloat has essentially been the norm for web applications, but
					now there is a better solution! The Shared Libraries WAR format reduces your application&rsquo;s deployment footprint and
					eradicates library bloat by allowing you to declare dependencies on libraries via standard OSGi manifest headers
					such as
					<literal>Import-Package</literal>
					and
					<literal>Require-Bundle</literal>
					. The @short.product.name@ provides additional support for simplifying dependency management via the
					<literal>Import-Library</literal>
					and
					<literal>Import-Bundle</literal>
					manifest headers which are essentially macros that get expanded into OSGi-compliant
					<literal>Import-Package</literal>
					statements.
				</para>
				<tip>
					<para>
						For detailed information on which libraries are already available, check out the
						<ulink url="http://www.springsource.com/repository">@ebr@
						</ulink>
						.
					</para>
				</tip>
			</section>
			<section id="architecture-shared-services-war">
				<title>Shared Services WAR</title>
				<para>
					Once you&rsquo;ve begun taking advantage of declarative dependency management with a Shared Libraries WAR, you&rsquo;ll likely
					find yourself wanting to take the next step toward reaping further benefits of an OSGi container: sharing services
					between your OSGi-compliant bundles and your web applications. By building on the power and simplicity of
					Spring-DM, the
					<emphasis>Shared Services WAR</emphasis>
					format puts the OSGi Service Registry at your finger tips. As a best practice you&rsquo;ll typically publish services
					from your domain, service, and infrastructure bundles via
					<literal>&lt;osgi:service ... /&gt;</literal>
					and then consume them in your web application&rsquo;s ApplicationContext via
					<literal>&lt;osgi:reference ... /&gt;</literal>.
					Doing so promotes programming to interfaces and allows you to completely decouple your web-specific deployment
					artifacts from your domain model, service layer, etc., and that&rsquo;s certainly a step in the right direction. Of the
					three supported WAR deployment formats, the Shared Services WAR is by far the most attractive in terms of
					modularity and reduced overall footprint of your web applications.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section id="architecture-war-rfc66">
				<title>WARs and the OSGi Web Container (RFC66)</title>
				<para>
					@product.name@ fully supports the OSGi Web Container (RFC66) standard. In fact, the reference implementation for RFC66 
					was developed by SpringSource from an offshoot of the original @short.product.name@ codebase. This RI is now fully integrated in
					@short.product.name@ as the basis of the support for web application deployment. 
				</para>
				<para>
					The Web Container specification introduces the concept of a <emphasis>web bundle</emphasis>, which is a WAR that is also
					a bundle. The specification defines how WAR files are transformed into bundles automatically as needed. 
				</para>
				<para>
					The Web Container specification is not yet publicly available, but you can find an introduction to the Web Container in
					blog entries written by the @short.product.name@ team 
					<ulink url="http://blog.springsource.com/2009/05/27/introduction-to-the-osgi-web-container/">here</ulink> 
					and <ulink url="http://blog.springsource.com/2009/06/01/what-the-osgi-web-container-means-for-dm-server/">here</ulink>.
				</para>
				<section id="architecture-war-rfc66-extensions">
					<title>Extensions to the Web Container</title>
					<para>
						@product.name@ provides a variety of extensions to the Web Container that allow you to construct sophisticated applications.
						The table below, summarizes the extensions that are available or in development.
					</para>
					<table colsep="1" rowsep="3">
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec width="1*"/>
							<colspec width="1*"/>
							<colspec width="1*"/>
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry>Feature</entry>
									<entry>Description</entry>
									<entry>Notes</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>Auto-import of system packages</entry>
									<entry>All packages exported by the system bundle are automatically imported by web bundles</entry>
									<entry>This feature is being discussed for inclusion in the specification</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>Instrumentable ClassLoaders</entry>
									<entry>All web bundle ClassLoaders are instrumentable by Spring&rsquo;s load-time weaving infrastructure.</entry>
									<entry></entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>Support for exploded bundles/WARs</entry>
									<entry>Bundles/WARs in directory form can be deployed as web bundles</entry>
									<entry></entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>Support for scanning TLDs in dependencies</entry>
									<entry>As per the Web Container specification, all TLDs located inside a web bundle are located using the rules 
									defined in the JSP 2.1 specification. In @short.product.name@, the dependencies of a web bundle are also scanned 
									for TLDs following the rules outlined in JSP 2.1</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</table>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section id="architecture-web-modules">
			<title>Web Modules</title>
			<para>
				Web Modules have been removed in favor of war files and web bundles following the OSGi Web Container specification.
				We believe our users will benefit more from a standard model than one that is @short.product.name@-specific.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="architecture-pars">
			<title>PAR</title>
			<para>
				A PAR is a standard JAR which contains all of the modules of your application (e.g., service,
				domain, and infrastructure bundles as well as a WAR or web module for web applications) in a single deployment unit.
				This allows you to deploy, refresh, and undeploy your entire application as a single entity. If you are familiar with Java
				EE, it is worth noting that a PAR can be considered a replacement for an EAR (Enterprise Archive) within the context
				of an OSGi container. As an added bonus, modules within a PAR can be refreshed independently and on-the-fly, for
				example via the @product.name@ Tool Suite (see <xref linkend="tooling" />).
			</para>
			<para>
				Many of the benefits of the PAR format are due to the underlying OSGi infrastructure, including:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para> Fundamentally modularized applications: instead of relying on fuzzy boundaries between logical modules
						in a monolithic application, this style promotes physically separated modules in the form of OSGi bundles. Then
						each module may be developed separately, promoting parallel development and loose coupling.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para> Robust versioning of various modules: the versioning capability offered by OSGi is much more
						comprehensive than any alternatives. Each module can specify a version range for each of its dependencies. Bundles
						are isolated from each other in such a way that multiple versions of a bundle may be used simultaneously in an
						application.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para> Improved serviceability: each bundle may be deployed or undeployed in a running application. This allows
						modifying the existing application to fix bugs, improve performance, and even to add new features without having
						to restart the application.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para> Furthermore, PARs scope the modules of your application within the @short.product.name@. Scoping provides both a
				physical and logical application boundary, effectively shielding the internals of your application from other PARs deployed
				within the @short.product.name@. This means your application doesn&rsquo;t have to worry about clashing with other running
				applications (e.g., in the OSGi Service Registry). You get support for load-time weaving, classpath scanning, context class
				loading, etc., and the @short.product.name@ does the heavy lifting for you to make all this work seamlessly in an OSGi
				environment. If you want to take full advantage of all that the @product.name@ and OSGi have to offer, packaging and deploying
				your applications as a PAR is a good choice, although plans are an even better one, as described in the next section.</para>
			<tip>
				<title>OSGi != multiple JARs</title>
				<para>
					Note that while physically separated modules can, in theory, be implemented simply using multiple
					JARs, complex versioning requirements often make this impractical. For example,
					consider the situation depicted in the diagram below. 

					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>Bundle A depends on version 1.0.0 of bundle B and version 2.0.0 of bundle C.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Bundle B depends on version 1.0.0 of bundle C.</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>

					Suppose that versions 1.0.0 and 2.0.0 of bundle C are neither backward nor forward compatible. Traditional monolithic
					applications cannot handle such situations: either bundle A or bundle B would need reworking which undermines
					truly independent development. OSGi&rsquo;s versioning scheme enables this scenario to be implemented in a robust manner.
					If it is desirable to rework the application to share a single version of C, then this can be planned in and is not forced.
				</para>
				<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/architecture-bundle-versioning.png" /></imageobject></mediaobject>
			</tip>
		</section>
		<section id="architecture-plans">
			<title>Plans</title>
			<para>
				A plan is similar to a PAR in that it encapsulates all of the artifacts of your application in a single deployment unit. 
				The main difference, however, is that a plan is simply an XML file that lists the artifacts of your application; 
				a PAR, by contrast, is an actual JAR file that physically contains the artifacts.  
				Just like a PAR, you deploy, refresh, and undeploy a plan as a single entity. 
				We highly recommends the use of plans for creating applications.
			</para>
			<para>
				When you create a plan, you can specify that the included bundles and services are in a scope that isolates them 
				from the rest of @product.name@ 
				and its deployments. 
				This scoping ensures that the bundles wire to each other and see each other&rsquo;s services in preference to services 
				from outside the scope. 
				Scoping also prevents application code from leaking into the global scope or scope of another application. 
				In addition, a plan can link the lifecycle of a group of bundles together atomically, which ensures that install, 
				start, stop, and uninstall events 
				on a single artifact in the plan are escalated to all artifacts in the plan.  
				You can, however, disable both of these features by simply updating an attribute in the plan.
			</para>
			<para>
				The general benefits of using plans are similar to those of using PARs; see <link linkend="architecture-pars">PAR</link> for details.  
				Plans offer added benefits, however, such as the ability to control the deployment order of your application: 
				the order in which you list artifacts in the plan&rsquo;s XML file is the order in which @short.product.name@ deploys them.  
				Additionally, because plans specify the artifacts that make up an application by reference, it is easier to share content 
				between plans as well as update individual parts of a plan without having to physically repackage (re-JAR) it.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<!-- ======================================================================= -->

	<section id="architecture-dependency-types">
		<title>Dependency Types</title>
		<para>
			In an OSGi environment, there are two kinds of dependencies between various bundles: <emphasis>type</emphasis>
			dependency and <emphasis>service</emphasis> dependency.
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">Type dependency</emphasis>: A bundle may depend on a type exported by another
						bundle thus creating a type dependency. Type dependencies are managed through <literal>Import-Package</literal>
						and <literal>Export-Package</literal> directives in the OSGi manifest. This kind of dependency is similar
						to a JAR file using types in other JAR files from the classpath. However, as we&rsquo;ve seen earlier, there are
						significant differences.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">Service dependency</emphasis>: A bundle may also publish services (preferably using
						Spring-DM), and other bundles may consume those services. If two bundles depend on the same service, both
						will be communicating effectively to the same object. More specifically, any state for that service will
						be shared between all the clients of that service. This kind of arrangement is similar to the commonly
						seen client-server interaction through mechanisms such as RMI or Web Services.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<!-- ======================================================================= -->

	<section id="architecture-forming-bundles">
		<title>A guide to forming bundles</title>
		<para>
			So what makes a good application suitable for deployment on the @product.name@? Since OSGi is at the heart of the
			@short.product.name@, modular applications consisting of bundles, which each represent distinct functionality and
			well-defined boundaries, can take maximum advantage of the OSGi container&rsquo;s capabilities. The core ideas behind forming
			bundles require following good software engineering practices: separation of concerns, minimum coupling, and communication
			through clear interfaces. In this section, we look at a few approaches that you may use to create modular applications
			for @product.name@ deployment. Please consider the following discussion as guidelines and not as rules. 
		</para>
		<para> Bundles can be formed along horizontal slices of layering and vertical slices of function. The objective is to
			enable independent development of each bundle and minimize the skills required to develop each bundle.</para>
		<para>
			For example, an application could have the following bundles: <emphasis>infrastructure</emphasis>,
			<emphasis>domain</emphasis>, <emphasis>repository</emphasis>, <emphasis>service</emphasis>, and
			<emphasis>web</emphasis> as shown in the following diagram.</para>
		<para>
			<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/bundle-dependencies-layers.png" /></imageobject></mediaobject>
				
			Each bundle consists of types appropriate for that layer and exports packages and services to be used by other
			layers. Let&rsquo;s examine each bundle in more detail:
			<table id="architecture-forming-bundles-across-layers-table" colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="1">
				<title>Bundles across layers</title>
				<tgroup cols="5">
					<colspec colwidth="1*" />
					<colspec colwidth="2*" />
					<colspec colwidth="1*" />
					<colspec colwidth="1*" />
					<colspec colwidth="1*" />
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Bundles</entry>
							<entry>Imported Packages</entry>
							<entry>Exported Packages</entry>
							<entry>Consumed Services</entry>
							<entry>Published Services</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Infrastructure</entry>
							<entry>Third-party libraries</entry>
							<entry>Infrastructure interfaces</entry>
							<entry>None</entry>
							<entry>None</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Domain</entry>
							<entry>Depends: for example, if JPA is used to annotate persistent types, then JPA packages.</entry>
							<entry>Public domain types</entry>
							<entry>None</entry>
							<entry>None</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Web</entry>
							<entry>Domain, Service</entry>
							<entry>None</entry>
							<entry>Service beans</entry>
							<entry>None</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Service</entry>
							<entry>Domain, Infrastructure, Repository</entry>
							<entry>Service interfaces</entry>
							<entry>Repository beans</entry>
							<entry>Service beans</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Repository</entry>
							<entry>Domain, Third-party libraries, ORM bundles, etc.</entry>
							<entry>Repository interfaces</entry>
							<entry>DataSources, ORM session/entity managers, etc.</entry>
							<entry>Repository beans</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</para>
		<para>
			Within each layer, you may create bundles for each subsystem representing a vertical slice of business functionality.
			For example, as shown in the following figure, the service layer is divided into two bundles each representing
			separate business functionalities.
			<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/bundle-dependencies-verticals.png" /></imageobject></mediaobject>
		</para>
		<para> You can similarly separate the repositories, domain classes, and web controllers based on the business role
			they play.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
