<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
		"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="common-libraries">
	<title>Working with Common Enterprise Libraries</title>
    <titleabbrev>Common Libraries</titleabbrev>
	<section id="common-libraries-spring">
		<title>Working with Spring</title>
		<section id="common-libraries-spring-bundor-template">
			<title>Importing Spring in a Bundlor Template</title>
				<para>
					It is good practice to restrict the version of Spring packages that your application imports to a suitable version range.
					This can be achieved by adding the following, for example, to a Bundlor <filename>template.mf</filename> file:
		<programlisting><![CDATA[Import-Template: 
		 org.springframework.*;version="[3.0.0, 3.1.0)"]]>
		</programlisting>
					(Be careful not to leave trailing spaces on lines or insert blank lines in this file. An exception is that there
					must be one trailing space after the header's colon to indicate that the header continues on the next line.)
				</para>
		</section>
		<section id="common-libraries-spring-component-scanning">
			<title>Enabling Component Scanning</title>
			<para>
				Spring will detect annotations such as <classname>@Controller</classname> and create a bean of controller type, 
				<emphasis>provided that</emphasis> it scans the classpath for these.
				Spring&rsquo;s component scanning is enabled by inserting a <literal>context</literal> tag 
				in one of the Spring bean definition files.
			</para>
			<para>
				For example, the Greenpages sample has a file <filename>WEB-INF/greenpages-servlet.xml</filename> in the
				<literal>src/main/webapp</literal> folder containing the following lines:
	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[	<!-- enable classpath scanning -->
		<context:component-scan base-package="greenpages.web" />]]>
	</programlisting>
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="common-libraries-hibernate">
		<title>Working with Hibernate</title>
		<section id="common-libraries-hibernate-import">
			<title>Importing Hibernate</title>
			<para>
				Hibernate uses CGLIB to dynamically create subclasses of your entity types at
				runtime. To guarantee that Hibernate and CGLIB can correctly see the types,
				you must add an <literal>Import-Library</literal> or <literal>Import-Bundle</literal> for the Hibernate library or bundle
				into any bundle that uses Hibernate directly.
			</para>
			<para>
			      	Additionally, if other bundles in your application contain types to be persisted by Hibernate, then be sure to specify the <code>import-scope</code> directive of the <literal>Import-Bundle</literal> header in the bundle that uses Hibernate directly.  The <literal>import-scope</literal> directive tells @tomcat.product.name@ to implicitly import the bundle into all other bundles that make up the application; this ensures that bundles that indirectly depend on the generated Hibernate classes have access to them, but you do not have to explicitly update their <code>Import-Bundle</code> header, ensuring modularity.  For example:
			</para>
	           <programlisting>
Import-Bundle: com.springsource.org.hibernate;version="[3.2.6.ga,3.2.6.ga]";<emphasis role="bold">import-scope:=application</emphasis></programlisting>
		<para>
			The <code>import-scope</code> directive works only for the bundles in a scoped application (PARs or plans.)
		</para>

		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="common-libraries-datasources">
		<title>Working with DataSources</title>
		<para>
			Many <literal>DataSource</literal> implementations use the <literal>DriverManager</literal>
			class which is incompatible with typical OSGi class loading semantics. To get around this,
			use a <literal>DataSource</literal> implementation that does not rely on
			<literal>DriverManager</literal>. Versions of the following
			<literal>DataSources</literal> that are known to work in an OSGi environment are available in the
			<ulink url="http://www.springsource.com/repository">@ebr@</ulink>.
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<ulink url="http://www.springsource.com/repository/app/bundle/detail?name=com.springsource.org.apache.commons.dbcp">Apache Commons DBCP</ulink>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>SimpleDriverDataSource available in
					<ulink url="http://www.springsource.com/repository/app/bundle/detail?name=org.springframework.jdbc">Spring JDBC</ulink>
					2.5.5 and later
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section id="common-libraries-weaving-instrumentation">
		<title>Weaving and Instrumentation</title>
		<para>
			When using a library that performs bytecode weaving or instrumentation, such as AspectJ,
			OpenJPA or EclipseLink, any types that are woven must be able to see the library doing
			the weaving. This is accomplished by adding an <literal>Import-Library</literal> for the
			weaving library into all bundles that are to be woven.
		</para>
		<para>
			Weaving is often used by JPA implementations to transform persisted types. When using a
			JPA provider that uses load-time weaving, an <literal>Import-Library</literal> for the
			provider is needed in the bundles containing the persisted types.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="common-libraries-tld">
		<title>JSP Tag Libraries</title>
		<para>
			When using tag libraries within a WAR or Web Bundle, be sure to include an
			<literal>Import-Bundle</literal> or <literal>Import-Library</literal> for the tag library
			bundle(s). This will ensure that your module can see the TLD definition and implementing types.
			For example, to use the Apache implementation of JSTL, add the following to your bundle&rsquo;s
			<literal>/META-INF/MANIFEST.MF</literal>:
		</para>
<programlisting>
<emphasis role="bold">Import-Bundle</emphasis>: com.springsource.org.apache.taglibs.standard;version="1.1.2"
</programlisting>
	</section>
</chapter>
